All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about, Kubernetes
networking at a very high level.
Understand,
the architectural benefits that are there
and the flexibility that you get by using,
Kubernetes networking.
Again, this is just a primer.
There's several books that have been
written about, Kubernetes networking,
interesting reads and, different design
patterns are discovered in those.
So fundamentally, the fundamental model
that's used is a flat pod network,
which means
if every pod gets a unique IP
routable IP address
and that pods communicate
directly with each other,
with no Nat in the middle.
So container,
sits on an individual pod, and I can have
multiple containers in the pod.
Right.
But a pod itself receives
a unique routable
IP address
that is, is one of the key, tenants.
The other
other key tenants in here are service
abstraction, which means that I can define
a service,
independent of the IP addresses.
This gives me the flexibility
of having services know about each other
without having to map directly
to an IP address.
That mapping is done on the back end,
through your DNS or cluster IP, concept.
Right.
And then there are other key
aspect here is network policy.
So network policy allows me to define pod
to pod traffic
to namespaces, labels
other policies, port port addresses.
This gives me the ability
to really enforce, security.
I can lock it down very tightly.
And it's all enforced by CNI plugins.
Or EB, P4 layers.
So the good thing about the CNI plug ins,
there's lots of them out there.
And, I can set up different network
topologies
and design patterns based off of those.
So really simple, example
we talked about in previous lecture
on Kubernetes architecture.
Go check that one out that every worker
node has something called a kubelet.
This is really kind of a controller
on setting up.
Or maybe it's an agent
that's run, by the master controllers,
but it's really, setting up the pods
and, setting up the network
so that these pods can talk to each other.
So simply put, it can add a CNI plug
in, into the worker node.
And, you'll want the same plug in
for all of your nodes, right.
Because it's going to set up different,
networking topologies
for you or networking, philosophies.
And then what happens is when I add a pod,
a network
namespace gets created
based off of those plug ins.
And remember,
every pod gets a Nick IP address
and it sets up that virtual link.
But between the virtual Ethernet device
and the Ethernet device that's running
inside the pod, which is really kind of
like a little tiny virtual machine,
but it is a namespace in there
where I can run multiple containers.
Right?
All of the configurability
is stored in your,
Etsy, CNI, network a directory
so you can find
all that information in there.
And then also I can talk
to the host network through the bridge
or an overlay network.
Just like we find
in Docker and Docker Swarm.
One of the
big differences that you should know about
is the, ability
to extend the network
easily in Kubernetes over Docker Swarm.
Docker swarm is highly opinionated,
which means it's easy to set up,
but you're stuck with what they chose.
With Kubernetes, a little more set up,
but you can choose
several different,
networking topologies and configurability.
You can get into really fine
grained, control.
So we've already talked about
some of the C in CNI plug ins.
I got calico which does BGP
routing flannel,
which is probably the easiest to set up,
which is Vxlan overlay,
very similar to Docker Swarm.
It's an overlay network,
with a net is a mesh overlay.
And then I have cilium which is an EVP.
It can handle, level three two, level
seven networking and security.
Level seven.
You're going to see level
seven use a lot with service meshes,
which we'll talk about later.
On each node I got his CNI.
And to create the network namespace
and the virtual Ethernet pair
that's required for the container to talk
to, the host
and to anything else
side of the container.
Right. And that's, that's the goal here.
Remember, every pod is assigned
an IP address and a root.
And that's unique to that pod.
So let's talk about the service
networking.
So service
networking is at the application layer.
So the idea here is that I can specify
dependencies between services
and connectivity between services by name
instead of by having to know
and resolve the name,
to an IP address that's handled for me
underneath the covers,
from the service, mesh
that's been created.
The important thing about this
is this gives me flexibility.
And more specifically, reliability.
If the service goes down,
ends up on a different pod,
the IP address is going to change.
I don't really care.
Because all of the traffic
is going to that service mesh,
which, it is going to route it
to the appropriate
IP address and the appropriate container
that's running.
If you are debugging
an individual container,
this can get a little hairy sometimes.
Container running right.
Because, if your connectivity goes down
and all of a sudden
you won't be getting messages anymore,
and, and everything is highly resilient.
So it will keep running
by spinning up new pods or connecting new
pods, with, those new containers.
Okay.
Service networking, key concepts
here is a cluster IP.
This is a virtual IP.
That's accessible
only inside the cluster.
This, is very similar to microservice,
segmentation
in that only inside the cluster
can you access the pods, individually.
Pod pot.
Right on on this cluster IP.
Namespace that, that is there.
Your kube proxy,
which we talked about in the,
Kubernetes architecture
lecture, is running on the worker nodes.
It's handling all of that, for you.
Right.
It also will handle load
balancing of traffic across, a service.
If you've got a service
running on a single machine, it will,
it will, load balance
across the pods on that machine.
If it's across multiple machines,
it will do the same thing.
It will forward things on a node port.
Is the individual ports
that are accessible to that node.
It's a static port on every single
node of that gives me external access.
Load balancer, as you already know.
Gives me a public IP address,
so people can send me requests.
I can, I can
then send it inside, the, cluster.
And most of this comes through an ingress
network, and there's lots of different,
configurability
that is available through the ingress.
And there's also ingress controllers
that you can use.
You can plug in your all weather's
interconnects, traffic or homegrown one.
This is different than Docker Swarm,
which has one baked in.
And this one you can develop your own
and have very complex routing rules
or whatever you want to do.
Here's another thing
that's been added is DNS and discovery.
This is, really, critical.
If you want your services
to know about each other.
And, this, gives me ability
to, call from one service
to another based off of a name or service
or attributes,
on those names, depending on which,
architecture that you're using.
They all get mapped to this in Kubernetes.
They got a Q cube, cube, a DNS,
which, can handle
all the in
cluster DNS, routing that you need.
There's also headless services
that you can create,
where there's no cluster IP on them.
The DNS returns pod IPS directly
from the client side, load balancing.
So I can circumvent the, load balancing.
That's built into Kubernetes by doing,
by doing this, if I want to use
an external load balancer, against,
client pods that are sitting there.
All right.
Network policies,
just real quick, network policies,
are highly configurable and that's what
you would expect with Kubernetes, right.
Configure
configurability over convenience, right.
Because I may want to lock down my cluster
very tightly, in which I can say, pod
A can only talk to pod B through this
set of ports,
in highly secure environments.
You may want to do that.
In other environments
where things are more dynamic
and you need more resilience
than security, you may do some trade
offs there on how tight
you lock these policies down.
We're not going to go in the depth
of all the network policies
that would take
several hours of lectures.
You can go discover
more of that on your own.
Remember we
mentioned before that we've got, cluster
IP that's like a micro segmented network
inside a cluster.
No one from the outside can attach.
Well, what if I have multiple clusters
running across a vast,
architecture, a distributed architecture
or multiple clouds
or whatever the case may be?
Multi-Cluster there are some approaches.
One is a service mesh mesh approach.
It's, you know, multi clusters,
are are great options for that.
I've got global DNS and mesh
where I've got linker D and console
where I can address
services across multiple clusters.
And then I've got a network,
fabric extensions
for like Sub-Mariner
where I want to do direct pod
networks across multiple clusters,
which could be very interesting as well.
So as I mentioned before, true Banettes
really gives me a lot of flexibility.
So with all that flexibility
comes a lot of power.
So we need some best practices. So first
pick the CNI
that matches your scale
and security needs.
Understand about the different CNI I's
and what their benefits and cons are.
Maybe I'll, put together a lecture on,
analysis of the different carries,
so that you can pick which one you need
for, the type of architecture and working
operating environment that you're in.
Always use network policies
to enforce a least privilege.
Don't leave it wide open, even though
there may be a temptation to do that.
That's how you get, cyber attack,
right?
Use a headless services only for stateful
sets on client side balancing.
All right.
If I got my own, I got several
clients coming in, and I want to
do my load
balancing external to be, cluster.
I can do that.
With these headless services.
Make sure you're monitoring your networks
both inside and outside of the cluster.
And look for drop packets and throughput
problems that you may be having.
You may need to make some adjustments
to your architecture and maybe even your,
scalability, configurations
on those and then, test,
test your network settings,
by when using overlays,
your interview settings.
Sorry, your interview settings,
I mean, using overlays,
it does add a little bit,
but it's like 50 bytes of information.
Okay.
I hope that, you understand
kind of the key concepts here.
Remember unified, there's a unified
IP per pod model in Kubernetes.
It offers secure service endpoints
through the flexibility
that it has to spin up new pods to handle
when pods go down.
Make sure that, you are programing
your network policies,
make sure those are put into place
and always select the right CNI plug in.
That's
that's really, the most important things.